

DIRECTOR OF ENGINEERING

Bangalore, India

🛮 🖰 (+91) 9500083139 | 🗷 aameer.rafiq@gmail.com | 🎁 aameer.github.io | 🖸 aameer | 🛅 aameerwani | 🐚 aameer

Summary_

I love startups & I am a huge fan of entrepreneurs. I love to learn and innovate new things with researchers, hackers and most importantly with dreamers. I have a decade of experience in leading engineering, product and design teams at high paced technology startups.

Stack_

Django, python, Javascript, Go, Shell scripting, Linux, PostgreSQL, Nginx, Celery, Supervisor, Gunicorn, Bento, ffmpeg, Bootstrap, nodejs, AngularJS, HTML5, Rest API's, Mongo DB, API Gateway, MySQL, MPEG Dash, Hls, Drm, Jira, Twilio, Asana, Bitbucket, Git, CSS, Liquid, C, C++, Kineticjs, Shopify, VueJs, AWS with some exposure to Azure, Google cloud, Kubernetes, flutter as well.

Work Experience _

GlobalFair Inc.

Bangalore, India

Jan. 2023 - Present

DIRECTOR OF TECHNOLOGY/ AVP OF TECHNOLOGY

- Leading Product, Technology and Design divisions at GlobalFair. A Series-A startup in building materials supply chain space. Some achievements from our charter are listed below.
- We automated PI creation up to 99% **resulting in TAT drop of 60X, while reducing errors by 88.6%.** Estimated average error cost to the organisation \$28000.
- We were successful in reducing sample matching time from **30 days to 2 minutes Al**.
- We pioneered catalog standardisation (supplier GF client) as novel approach in industry resulting in moat for the Organisation.
- Lead a cultural shift across tech, product and design divisions resulting in reduction of issues by 83.4% and PI breakages by 5x.
- Implemented lean methodologies resulting in 84% adherence to planned releases.
- Successfully Integrated with external e.g services QuickBooks, Roambee, Searates, hubspot etc.
- Developed analytics wing to lead data driven decision making across the org and introduction of live KPIs.
- Cross departmental initiatives resulted in Increased departmental adherence from around 1% to 80%.
- We increased app adoption from 9.38% to 40.63%.
- · We increased monthly active users by 65%.
- · Lead design team to introduce new design language at GF.

Udaan.comBangalore, India

ASSOCIATE DIRECTOR OF ENGINEERING

Sep. 2021 - Dec 2022

- Improved the CM3 burn for Fresh by 10X on a war footing by tuning technology for business use case while keeping unit economics in mind.
- Spear headed Introduction of Catch-weight (bill user as per weight) in Udaan, making it first B2B in India to do so. This alone resulted in 2% gain in GMV.
- Reduced net overall wastage from **6.23% to 2.65%** within a quarter by technology interventions on supply chain.
- Optimised TAT's by re-imagining the automated guardrails e.g IRN to GI resulting in TAT reduction from 15.89 to 0.4 hrs.
- Systematised collection centres of Udaan within a quarter (from scratch) with **best in class payment TATs of within 2 hrs**. Lead all phases of product development requirements gathering, competitive analysis, PRD's, architecture, implementation and release.
- · Lead Facilities-Inbound Engineering sub cluster at Udaan across all categories. Lead platforming initiatives to refactor legacy code.
- Plugged product/technical leakages with reduction in Mario RTV from 45% to 61%.
- Reduction in Technical escalation by 57% while scale increased by 12%.
- Reduction in returns by because of Infestation by 34.9%.

Indee.tv Bangalore, India

LEAD ENGINEERING/FOUNDING ENGINEER/ISO

Mar. 2015 - 2021

- Experience of interviewing 1000's of candidates and hiring 10x engineers, managing enterprise clients and reporting directly to CEO.
- Built a Multi-DRM system. Supports **Widevine**, **Fairplay**, **PlayReady** and a **Forensic watermarking** system on the cloud which form the core IP of Indee.
- Developed a Real Time Analytics system which tracks user's per-second video engagement.
- Web security Software systems which I have build have withstood tests from one of the best white hat hackers in the world. I tend to think about security at each level of the architecture and I do not limit myself to just focusing on secure code.
- Developed a **cloud transcoding system** on AWS and achieved horizontal scaling with it **at approximately 10x lower cost** compared to the competition i.e services like AWS elastic trans-coder, AWS elemental and Zencoder.
- Achieved fast and secure uploads which supports more than 10GB file size uploads within minutes directly from browser to S3. Almost **2X fast** compared to other services in this domain with almost **2X the support for file size**.
- Responsible for overall security as I also served as an Information security officer. Lead quarterly security audits, fixes and drafted policies.
- Responsible for design of an overall service architecture and pipelines. Lead quick prototyping methodology for R&D. Product experiencing growth of more than 20% month over month.
- · Experience in working with auditing teams of large corporations and delivering on SLA's of 99.99% availability.

Imaginate. Hyderabad, India

SOFTWARE ENGINEER Sep. 2013 - Mar. 2015

- lead the engineering efforts at Imaginate for design and development of Dressy API(B2B), Shopify App, Dressy(B2C).
- Dressy led us to be the winner of Next B2B Startup 2014 -The World Economic Forum
- Built Javascript libraries for easy clients Integration with dressy's and enable virtual trail on.
- Successful exit as Dressy was bought over by Aditya Birla Group.

Honors & Awards

2012 MOMA Scholar India, For exemplary academic performance by Government of India.

Srinagar India Srinagar, India

2012 **3rd Rank - Bronze Medalist**, University of Kashmir - B.E CSE 2012

Delhi, India

2011 **Topped the Batch,** Hp Networking Certification

Publication

Augmented reality for fire and emergency services.

Hyderabad, India

INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON RECENT TRENDS IN COMMUNICATION AND COMPUTER NETWORKS.

IDES Issn 2214-1464 - ComNet 2013

• Proposes a system to improve collaboration and help first responders using AR.

Education

University Of Kashmir

Srinagar, India

B.E IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

Dec. 2008 - Dec. 2012

• Cofounded UAF group.